Guide to the Gerrit Smith Miller papers, 1878-1937
Smith, Gerrit Miller papers, 1878-1937
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gerrit Smith Miller papers, 1878-1937.
3700
Gerrit Smith Miller, 1845-1937.
4 cubic ft.
Correspondence and financial records.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Gerrit Smith Miller was a cattle breeder who developed the Holstein-Friesian cattle breeding industry in the United States. He was a member of the New York State Legislature in 1880, and held several other positions as a public official. Collection includes extensive correspondence with his friends and family members.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Gerrit Smith Miller was a cattle breeder who developed the Holstein-Friesian cattle breeding industry in the United States. He was a member of the New York State Legislature in 1880, and held several other positions as a public official.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes extensive correspondence with his friends and family members, including his sons and daughters-in-law: Gerrit Smith Miller, Jr. and Anne Gates Miller; Basil Dixwell Miller and June Miller; William DeYough and Bertha F.W. Field; Alfred G. and Daisy Lewis; Edward B. and Lorna Watson; James D'Wolf and Alice Lovett; Hattie Lovett Brooks; Esther B. Owen; Arria D. Owen; Jacob G. Smith (Cornell University Class of 1903); Edith Hamilton White; and many others, which documents his family and social life, as well as his active support of the Piney Woods Country Life School, Livingstone College and Industrial School for Colored Young Men and Women, Tuskegee Institute, and the George Junior Republic. Also, correspondence with Charles H. Baldwin, Frank N. Decker, M.S. Prescott, Jared Van Wagenen, Stanton D. Wicks, and others which documents his varied business interests, mainly his pioneering role in the development of the Holstein Breed of cattle in America and his active participation in the Holstein-Friesian Association of America; and financial records, including receipts and statements relating to household expenses, taxes, investments and charitable contributions, journals recording daily expenses and income, account books showing expenditures for wood and wages, and a ledger giving information on Miller's income.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Miller, Gerrit Smith, 1845-1937.; Baldwin, Charles H.; Brooks, Hattie Lovett.; D'Wolf, James.; Decker, Frank N.; DeYough, William.; Field, Bertha F.W.; Lewis, Alfred G.; Lewis, Daisy.; Lovett, Alice.; Miller, Anne Gates.; Miller, Basil Dixwell.; Miller, Gerrit Smith, Jr.; Miller, June.; Owen, Arria D.; Owen, Esther B.; Prescott, M.S.; Smith, Jacob G.; Van Wagenen, Jared, 1871-1960.; Watson, Edward B.; Watson, Lorna.; White, Edith Hamilton.; Wicks, Stanton D.; George Junior Republic (Freeville, N. Y.).; Holstein-Friesian Association of America.; Livingstone College and Industrial School for Colored Young Men and Women.; Piney Woods School.; Tuskegee Institute.
Subjects:
Education.; Cattle--Breeding.; Animal culture.; Holstein-Friesian cattle.; Cattle breeders.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, Sept. 9, 1927 - Dec. 31, 1927, A-F (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Sept. 9, 1927 - Dec. 31, 1927, G-M (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Sept. 9, 1927 - Dec. 31, 1927, N-T (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Sept. 9, 1927 - Dec. 31, 1927, U-Z (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Oct. 16, 1931 - Mar. 4, 1932, A-D (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Oct. 16, 1931 - Mar. 4, 1932, E-J (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Oct. 16, 1931 - Mar. 4, 1932, K-R (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, Oct. 16, 1931 - Mar. 4, 1932, S-Z (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1, 1933 - June 10, 1933, A-D (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1, 1933 - June 10, 1933, E-J (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1, 1933 - June 10, 1933, K-M (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1, 1933 - June 10, 1933, N-T (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, Jan. 1, 1933 - June 10, 1933, U-Z (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, A-C (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, D-H (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, I-L (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, M-O (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, P-T (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, June 10, 1933 - Feb. 27, 1934, U-Z (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, Feb. 28, 1934 - Sept. 4, 1934, A-E (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, Feb. 28, 1934 - Sept. 4, 1934, F-J (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, Feb. 28, 1934 - Sept. 4, 1934, K-L (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, Feb. 28, 1934 - Sept. 4, 1934, M-O (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, Feb. 28, 1934 - Sept. 4, 1934, P-Z (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, Sept. 1934 - Feb. 1935, A-F (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, Sept. 1934 - Feb. 1935, G-L (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, Sept. 1934 - Feb. 1935, M-O (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, Sept. 1934 - Feb. 1935, P-Z (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, Feb. 13, 1935 - Aug. 5, 1935, A-F (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Feb. 13, 1935 - Aug. 5, 1935, G-L (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Feb. 13, 1935 - Aug. 5, 1935, M-O (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Feb. 13, 1935 - Aug. 5, 1935, P-Z (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1935 -1936, A-I (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1935 -1936, J-Z (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1935 -1936, Misc. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, June 3, 1936 - Oct. 27, 1936, A-J (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, June 3, 1936 - Oct. 27, 1936, K-Z (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, June 3, 1936 - Oct. 27, 1936, Misc. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, June 3, 1936 - Oct. 27, 1936, Misc. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Oct. 27, 1936 - Feb. 5, 1937, A-F (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, Oct. 27, 1936 - Feb. 5, 1937, G-J (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, Oct. 27, 1936 - Feb. 5, 1937, K-M (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, Oct. 27, 1936 - Feb. 5, 1937, N-Z (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, Feb. 5, 1937 - Apr. 19, 1937, A-L (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, Feb. 5, 1937 - Apr. 19, 1937, M-Z (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Farm, 1925 -1929, A-D (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Farm, 1925 -1929, E-L (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Farm, 1925 -1929, M-Z (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Fire, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Fire, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Fire, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Income tax returns, 1913 -1927 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Income tax returns, 1913 -1927 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Receipts, ca. 1928 -1931, A-C (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Receipts, ca. 1928 -1931, D-F (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Receipts, ca. 1928 -1931, G-H (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Receipts, ca. 1928 -1931, I-O (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Receipts, ca. 1928 -1931, P-Z (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Receipts, ca. 1930 -1932, A-C (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Receipts, ca. 1930 -1932, D-F (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Receipts, ca. 1930 -1932, G-J (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Receipts, ca. 1930 -1932, K-R (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Receipts, ca. 1930 -1932, S-Z (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Receipts, 1932, A-Z (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Receipts, 1932 -1936, A-E (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Receipts, 1932 -1936, F-K (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Receipts, 1932 -1936, L-M (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Receipts, 1932 -1936, N-Z (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Receipts, 1933 -1936, A-E (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Receipts, 1933 -1936, F-K (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Receipts, 1933 -1936, L-M (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Receipts, 1933 -1936, N-Z (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Receipts, 1934 -1936, A-G (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Receipts, 1934 -1936, H-M (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Receipts, 1934 -1936, N-S (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Receipts, 1934 -1936, T-Z (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Receipts, 1934 -1936, Misc. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Receipts, 1935 -1936, A-Z (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Receipts, 1935 -1936, Misc. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Receipts, 1936 -1937, A-L (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Receipts, 1936 -1937, M-Z (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Receipts, 1936 -1937, A-J (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Receipts, 1936 -1937, K-Z (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Receipts, 1936 -1937, Misc. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 42 diaries: 1878-1881, 1883, 1885, 1891-1893, 1895 -1908, 1910 -1925, 1927 -1928 (used for daily accounting) (Box 4)
- Account books
  - Wood, ca. 1903 -1904 (Box 4)
  - Employment, wages, ca. 1916 -1933 (Box 4)
  - Ledger, ca. 1902 -1927 (stocks, bonds, etc.) (Box 4)